In times gone by, one quarreled oft with Guizhong concerning mechanical principles
Eskiden, Guizhong'la mekanik prensipleri hakkında sık sık münakaşa ederdik.
We each had our ideals, and neither would yield
İkimizin de idealleri vardı ve asla geri adım atmazdık.
Under the pretext of a social gathering
Bir toplanma kisvesi altında
One invited the impartial Rex Lapis
Rex Lapis'i çağırdım
To judge the quality of our creations...
ve tarafsızca çıkardığımız işlerin kalitesi hakkında hakemlik yapmasını istedim...
But Rex Lapis declared
Fakat Rex Lapis
That Guizhong's Obscuro Vulpes Mechanism was superior
Guizhong'un Kara Tilki mekanizmasının daha üstün olduğunu ifade etti. Hıh...
Though one was too proud to acknowledge it, in one's heart, one knew
Gururum bunu itiraf etmeme izin vermese dahi
As for the story between Guizhong and Streetward Rambler
Guizhong ve Sokak Gezgini'nin hikayesine gelince
That begins with a certain bell
her şey bir çan ile başladı.
In Guizhong's opinion, while mechanisms were no substitute for human composers
Guizhong'a göre mekanizmalar insan bestecilerin yerini tutamazdı
They were yet capable of producing simple but fine melodies
fakat basit ve incelikli melodiler üretebilirlerdi.
But Streetward Rambler believed music to be an expression of the soul
Ancak Sokak Gezgini, müziğin ruhun bir ifadesi olduğuna
An emotional enterprise that could never hope to be replicated by machinery
ve makinalar tarafından taklit edilemeyecek kadar duygusal bir konu olduğuna inanırdı.
They argued endlessly, until one asked Rex Lapis to intercede
Durmadan süren tartışmalarına bir gün Rex Lapis müdahale etti.
He confiscated the bell, and designated it for ceremonial use
Çana el koydu ve sadece seremonilerde kullanılması için ayırdı.
Thereafter, one would often find them convening in the mountains
Bundan sonra onların sık sık dağlarda bir araya gelip
Discussing music, mechanics, and all the affairs of the mortal world
müzik, mekanik ve ölümlülerin dünyası hakkında konuştuklarını görürdüm.
But these good times were not to last
Fakat o güzel günler uzun sürmedi.
War broke out between the gods, and soon engulfed the Guili Plains
Tanrılar arasında savaş başladı ve kısa sürede Guili Ovası'nı ateş aldı.
Guizhong was overpowered by the enemy, and fell in battle
Guizhong düşman tarafından alt edildi ve savaşta düştü.
When Streetward Rambler and I arrived at the scene at long last, all that remained among the ruins... was her lifeless body
Sokak Gezgini ve ben onun yanına vardığımızda
After this, at Streetward Rambler's request
Bu olaydan sonra Sokak Gezgini'nin talebi üzerine
Rex Lapis granted her the Cleansing Bell for safekeeping
Rex Lapis ona saklaması için Arınma Çanını verdi.
To honor our friend's memory
Arkadaşımızın anısına
One made a few finishing touches to her ballistic device...
onun balistik cihazına son dokunuşları yaptım...
Many Lantern Rites have passed since then... many greetings and goodbyes
O günden bu yana çok sayıda Fener Şenliği oldu... Kimler geldi, kimler geçti...
Upon what do you gaze? The Guili Plains?
Neye bakıyorsun? Guili Ovası'na mı?
No, it's... everything
Hayır... Her şeye.
We think of human life as like a lantern that's lit one minute and extinguished the next, but are we adepti so different?
Bizler insan hayatını bir yanıp bir sönen fenerlere benzetiriz.
Perhaps, as dust settles after a storm
Belki de fırtına sakinleşip, ortalık durulduğunda
We too must one day return to the world below
bizim de diğer dünyaya göçme vaktimiz gelir.